Okay, so in this lesson, we're going to talk about two things that Claude Code can do, planning and thinking, which are both two very different things.Thinking is when you ask Claude Code to think about a solution before writing any code, and planning is when Claude puts together its own plan of action on how it intends to implement some features and asks you to approve it.So let's start with planning, and you might have caught a glimpse of this at the end of the last lesson where we used Alt+M to cycle through the auto-edit option down here.
好的，在這一課中，我們將討論 Claude Code 可以做的兩件事：規劃和思考，這是兩件截然不同的事情。思考是當你請 Claude Code 在撰寫任何程式碼之前先思考解決方案；而規劃是當 Claude 自行制定一個行動計劃，說明它打算如何實作某些功能，並要求你批准。讓我們從規劃開始，你可能在上一課結尾中瞥見過這個功能，我們使用 Alt+M 來循環切換下方的自動編輯選項。
So if I press Alt M once, I turn on the accept edits feature, but if I press it twice, we go into the planning mode instead.Now, planning mode is good for when you're giving Claude Code a task which has a wide breadth of changes over several different files, but where individually each of those changes might not necessarily be complex.They could be, but maybe not.Still, the scope of those changes might be quite wide and with a plan, it makes easier for Claude Code to stay on track and complete each task in order.
按一下 Alt+M，我開啟了「接受編輯」功能；但如果按兩下，我們就進入規劃模式。規劃模式適合用於交給 Claude Code 涉及多個不同檔案的大範圍修改任務，但其中每個個別的修改不一定複雜，可能是也可能不是。儘管如此，這些修改的範圍可能相當廣泛，有了計劃，Claude Code 就更容易保持在軌道上並依序完成每個任務。
Let's keep planning mode on and we're going to ask it to do the following.Can you make a custom component for an avatar?No pick, only initial and find any places in the project where it can replace avatar like templates.So I'm going to press enter now and see what it comes up with.
讓我們保持規劃模式開啟，請它完成以下任務：「你能製作一個自訂的頭像元件嗎？不需要圖片，只需要首字母，並找出專案中任何可以替換類似頭像範本的地方。」我現在要按 Enter，看看它會產生什麼結果。
So first of all, it's analysing the codebase to understand where an avatar component could be useful.So it's searching things, it's reading different files.
首先，它在分析程式碼庫，以了解頭像元件可能在哪些地方有用，它在搜尋、讀取不同的檔案。
All right, and now it's come up with a plan right here.So if we scroll to the top, you can see it's discovered avatar-like implementations in the blog system in a few different places, in the blog post cards, and also in recent activity in the sidebar.So it's detected those, and then it's proposing this avatar component.So it's in the correct place inside the UI folder, then an avatar folder, then avatar.tsx.So it's going to have
好了，它在這裡提出了一個計劃。往上捲動可以看到，它在部落格系統的幾個不同地方發現了類似頭像的實作：部落格文章卡片，以及側邊欄中的最近活動。它偵測到了這些地方，然後提議建立這個頭像元件，位置在 UI 資料夾裡的 avatar 資料夾中，檔案名稱為 avatar.tsx。
the initial based avatar, which is going to be the first letter from their name, multiple sizes, color variants, consistent styling.So it's kind of following the same pattern as the button component, which is nice.So for the implementation plan, it's going to first of all create the avatar component, then replace the existing avatar code in the blog post cards, and it even specifies exactly where it's going to do that for us.Then it says it's going to work on the blog sidebar,
它將具備以首字母為基礎的頭像（使用名字的第一個字母）、多種尺寸、顏色變體、一致的樣式風格，基本上遵循與按鈕元件相同的模式，這很好。關於實作計劃，它首先會建立頭像元件，然後替換部落格文章卡片中現有的頭像程式碼，並精確指定了要在哪裡進行替換。
and it's gonna add the avatar to individual blog posts as well inside the blog post details page.Then it's gonna create a test file to follow the existing button test patterns, so it can be tested on the avatar component as well.And then we're gonna add a link to the avatar preview in the header navigation.So you can go ahead and accept this plan, or you can accept the plan, but then keep manually approving any edits.
接著它說它將處理部落格側邊欄，並在部落格文章詳情頁面中也加入頭像。然後它要建立一個測試檔案，遵循現有的按鈕測試模式，讓頭像元件也能被測試。最後，我們要在標題列導覽中加入頭像預覽頁面的連結。
Or you can say no and keep planning and provide feedback for the plan so it adjusts the plan.So I'm going to select the first option up here, which is yes and auto accept edits.
你可以直接接受這個計劃，或者接受計劃但仍手動批准每個編輯，或者你可以說不，繼續規劃並提供回饋讓它調整計劃。我要選擇第一個選項：「是，並自動接受編輯」。
Okay, so down here it is saying it wants to run this bash command, npm run test.And I want to select the second option, which is yes, and don't ask me again for NPM run test commands.And when I do that, it should automatically go into the settings.local file right here, which we can see it does awesome.
好的，下面它表示想執行這個 Bash 指令：npm run test。我想選擇第二個選項：「是，且不再詢問 npm run test 指令」。這樣做後，它應該會自動加入到這裡的 settings.local 檔案中，我們可以看到確實如此，太棒了。
All right, so this time it's trying to link the file.And again, I'm going to choose the second option down here.
好了，這次它想要連結這個檔案，同樣地，我要選擇這裡的第二個選項。
Okay, then finally, it looks like it's done.So it's checked off everything from the plan it created.All the tests are passing.And if we close this off and take a look over here, we should be able to see that new avatar folder.And okay, so it's actually created a full page for the avatar.Now,Maybe that was in the plan and I didn't fully understand it.
好了，最後看起來它完成了，已將計劃中的所有事項全部打勾完成，所有測試都通過了。關閉這個後在這裡看看，應該就能看到那個新的 avatar 資料夾。好的，它實際上建立了一個完整的頭像頁面，也許這在計劃中有提到，但我沒有完全理解。
I thought it was just going to add it to the preview page, but you see this is where sometimes AI can go wrong, Claude Code, Copilot, whatever you're using, so it's important to keep it on track.Either way, it doesn't so much matter for this particular task.It's just to preview it after all, and I can delete this page afterwards.But you can see we've got this component folder down here, avatar.We've got the test file and the avatar component itself.So we've got the default size right here set to medium.
我以為它只是要把它加到預覽頁面，但有時候 AI 就是會出錯，不管是 Claude Code、Copilot 還是其他你使用的工具，所以讓它保持在軌道上很重要。不管怎樣，對於這個特定任務來說影響不大，畢竟只是用來預覽的，我可以之後刪除這個頁面。但你可以看到我們在這裡有 avatar 元件資料夾，還有測試檔案和頭像元件本身，預設尺寸設為 medium。
The variant is gradient, but we have these different variant options up here and different sizes as well for the props.We have the size classes, the variant classes, and then down here we have the avatar itself.Okay, so let's see if this works in the browser.All right, so you can see added the avatar page and the link to the header, so it did get a little bit trigger happy.And now if we take a look down here, we can see all the different variants that we have, the different sizes, even use cases down here.
樣式是 gradient，但在 props 中我們有這些不同的樣式選項和不同的尺寸選項。我們有尺寸 class、樣式 class，然後下面是頭像本身。好的，讓我們在瀏覽器中看看是否正常運作。好的，你可以看到它新增了頭像頁面和標題列中的連結，確實有點手癢過頭了。現在往下看，我們可以看到我們擁有的所有不同樣式、不同尺寸，甚至是這裡的使用案例。
So I think this is all really, really nice.It's created that component and shown us different ways we can use it.Now, if I go to the actual blog part of the website, you can see it's now using that avatar here, it's using it down here asinside recent activity, and if I was to select an individual blog like this one right here, you can see we have the avatar on the blog details as well.
我覺得這一切都非常非常棒，它建立了那個元件並向我們展示了不同的使用方式。現在，如果我去網站的部落格區塊，你可以看到它現在在這裡使用了那個頭像，在最近活動中也使用了它，如果我選擇像這篇這樣的個別部落格，你可以看到部落格詳情中也有頭像。
So the only thing it did really that I didn't want it to do was place the avatar link up here and create a full page for the avatars when I...specified in a claw.nd file that they should go inside the preview file.So maybe I wasn't specific enough, maybe I looked over the plan too quickly, I don't know.But this is easy to rectify, I can just delete these pages, no problem.
所以它真正做了我不想要的事情，只是把頭像連結放在上面，並建立了一個完整的頭像頁面，而我在 CLAUDE.md 檔案中指定了它們應該放在預覽頁面裡。也許我不夠具體，也許我看計劃時太快，我不知道。但這很容易修正，我只需刪除這些頁面就好，沒問題。
So I just told Claude Code to remove the avatar page and instead put all of the samples inside the preview page and it's going ahead and done that, which is good.I've also updated the Claude MD file with this more specific instruction at the bottom, which says now when making new page components, always add a link to that page in the header.So it did this for our UI component.So I added this bit on only do this for page components, not UI or other dropping components.So I guess this is a lesson in instructions.
我剛才告訴 Claude Code 刪除頭像頁面，改為將所有樣本放到預覽頁面中，它也照做了，很好。我也在 CLAUDE.md 檔案底部更新了這條更具體的指示，說明當建立新的頁面元件時，一律在標題列中加入該頁面的連結，所以它對我們的 UI 元件也這樣做了。於是我加了這一句：「只對頁面元件這樣做，不要對 UI 或其他元件這樣做。」我想這是一堂關於指示的課。
and also in how you have to be specific in what you want Claude code to do.Okay, so that'll work pretty well.And I think having plan mode turned on probably helped Claude code complete the task correctly.Now it may still have done so without planning mode on, but when it is turned on, I find it's worth to stay on track more for tasks with a wider scope.And arguably the scope wasn't huge for this task, but it still involved making a component, testing the component, looking for places it can be used, editing those files,
也是關於你必須如何具體說明你想要 Claude Code 做什麼的課。好的，這樣效果很好。我認為開啟規劃模式可能幫助 Claude Code 更正確地完成了任務。即使不開啟規劃模式它可能也會完成，但當它開啟時，我發現對於範圍更廣的任務，它更能保持在軌道上。可以說這個任務的範圍並不算很大，但它仍然涉及建立元件、測試元件、尋找可以使用它的地方、編輯那些檔案等等。
etc.Anyway, now let's look at thinking mode.Now think mode is good when you want Claude code to work on something that includes more complex logic.So not necessarily a wide scope like planning mode is for.It could be quite a narrow scope, but one where the logic is more complex.For example, I might want to implement a comment system for the blog where users can comment on the blogs and that would include perhaps some thoughts about exactly how it should be done, what auth services, if any, should be used.
無論如何，現在讓我們來看看思考模式。思考模式適合用於當你想要 Claude Code 處理包含更複雜邏輯的事情時，不一定是範圍很廣的任務（那是規劃模式的用途），而可能是範圍很窄但邏輯更複雜的任務。例如，我可能想為部落格實作一個留言系統，讓使用者可以在部落格上留言，這可能需要仔細思考應該如何具體實作、應該使用哪些認證服務（如果有的話）。
What React components need to be made?What additional pages might need to be made?What about live updates?And how does this get structured and fit well together in this application?So for something like this, you would turn on extended thinking mode, which does consume more tokens, but it allows the model to reason and think more about how to complete something in a way that actually works.Now, to be honest, we're entering into the realms of vibe coding when we ask the AI to implement a whole system like this, and I would personally break this
需要製作哪些 React 元件？可能需要製作哪些額外頁面？即時更新呢？以及這在這個應用程式中應如何架構並妥善整合？對於這樣的任務，你會開啟延伸思考模式，這確實會消耗更多 token，但它允許模型對如何以真正有效的方式完成某件事進行更深入的推理和思考。老實說，當我們請 AI 實作這樣一個完整的系統時，我們正在進入氛圍編程的領域。
down into smaller chunks or tasks and work on each one, one at a time with Claude code so I could more easily guide the AI to do what I want it to do.But for the sake of this lesson and to demonstrate thinking mode, we'll run with this example.So let me paste in this prompt right here, first of all, which says, implement a comment system into the application where users can authenticate and then comment on blog posts.Think hard about this implementation, including the database schema or
我個人會將其分解為更小的區塊或任務，與 Claude Code 一次處理一個，這樣我就能更輕鬆地引導 AI 做我想要的事情。但為了這一課並示範思考模式，我們先用這個例子。讓我在這裡貼入這個提示詞：「在應用程式中實作一個留言系統，讓使用者可以認證並在部落格文章上留言。請認真思考這個實作，包括資料庫結構或認證服務、審核和即時更新。」
authentication services, moderation and real-time updates.I'm also going to keep planning mode on so I can see the plan that Claude Code makes as well.Now I'm triggering think mode in this prompt by using the word think right here.And whenever Claude Code sees that in your prompt, that word, it's going to use extended thinking mode.So then let me press enter now and we'll see what Claude Code does.
我也要保持規劃模式開啟，這樣我也可以看到 Claude Code 制定的計劃。我在這個提示詞中使用了「think」這個詞來觸發思考模式，每當 Claude Code 在你的提示詞中看到那個詞，它就會使用延伸思考模式。現在讓我按 Enter，看看 Claude Code 會做什麼。
All right, so already in this kind of gray color, you can see it's thinking and this is the thinking process that it has kind of behind the scenes.So by using that think keyword in our prompt, we've enabled this thinking mode.
好的，在這個灰色區域中，你可以看到它正在思考，這是它在幕後的思考過程。透過在提示詞中使用 think 關鍵字，我們啟用了這個思考模式。
All right, and now it's come up with a plan.So that took a little bit longer, but it's because Claude code was thinking.So this is the plan and it's quite extensive, there's a lot of steps involved.All right, and anything in a kind of faded gray up here, this is all of Claude's thinking, and it also prefixes that, if you like, with this little thinking text right here, so every time it's thinking about something, you'll see that.All right, thinking, thinking.So it thinks quite a lot.
好了，它現在提出了一個計劃，花了更長一點的時間，但那是因為 Claude Code 在思考。這就是計劃，相當詳盡，涉及很多步驟。在這裡有點褪色的灰色，這都是 Claude 的思考過程，它也會在前面加上這個小小的「思考中」文字，所以每次它在思考某件事情時，你都會看到這個標示。好的，思考中，思考中，它確實思考了很多。
So then I'm not going to go ahead with these changes because that would drastically change my project right now.And I'd also have to set up some external services as well.And again, because I wouldn't normally let AI completely loose on tasks like this, I don't know which direction it's going to go off in.Instead, I would break it down into logical steps, maybe taking each of these checkpoints in the plan and working on them individually.That way I can stay in a loop, check the code in small steps manually, and make changes myself where I
所以我不打算繼續這些修改，因為這會大幅改變我現在的專案，我也必須設定一些外部服務。再次說明，因為我通常不會讓 AI 在這樣的任務上完全放飛自我，我不知道它會往哪個方向走偏。我寧願將其分解為合理的步驟，也許從計劃中的每個檢查點出發，逐一處理它們，這樣我就能保持在迴圈中，小步驟地手動檢查程式碼，並在需要時自行進行修改。
I need to along the way.Doing everything I want sometimes makes things harder in the long run.I find that pretty soon you're out of the loop and you get sucked into this full-on vibe coding experience where you're just asking Claw to fix everything and ignoring the code completely.I'm going to choose not to do this now, but just very quickly before we finish this video, I want to mention that Clawed code does have different levels of thinking that you can activate.In the example I just used, I said think hard.
讓 AI 一次做所有事情，有時從長遠來看會讓事情更難處理。我發現很快你就會脫離迴圈，被吸入那種全面的氛圍編程體驗，不斷請 Claude 修正一切，完全忽視程式碼本身。我現在選擇不這樣做。但在結束這部影片之前，我想快速提一下：Claude Code 有不同程度的思考模式可以啟用，在我剛才的例子中，我說了「think hard」（深度思考）。
But you can also just say think, and that's going to trigger a smaller amount of thinking and reasoning.Likewise, you can go the other way by saying think harder, and that's going to crank the thinking up even more.And if you want to go all in, then you can ask Claude to ultra think, which activates the hardest thinking mode it has.But again, remember that thinking consumes more tokens, and the harder you ask Claude code to think, the more tokens it's going to use up.All right then.
但你也可以只說「think」（思考），這會觸發較少量的思考和推理。同樣地，你可以往另一個方向，說「think harder」（更深度思考），這會讓思考程度更加強烈。如果你想全力以赴，則可以請 Claude「ultra think」（全力思考），這會啟用它最強的思考模式。但同樣要記住，思考會消耗更多 token，你請 Claude Code 思考得越深入，它消耗的 token 就越多。好了。
now we know a little bit about planning and thinking, next up we'll talk about commands.
現在我們對規劃和思考有了一些了解，接下來我們將討論指令。